This course is about the basic foundations of computer science, and there's nothing more foundational than numbers.
In order to do anything mathematical in computer science, our first order of business is to understand how computers handle numbers.
That's what this video is about.
By "number", for now we're only going to mean non-negative integers. An "integer" is simply a whole number, something that isn't a fraction or
decimal. So for the time being when we say "number" we mean 0, 1, 2, 3, and so on and we will leave negative numbers and fractions or
decimals out of the picture for now.
Let's think first about how we as human beings think about numbers. Look at the number 275. When you were a kid, you learned that this
number has three digits -- the 2, the 7, and the 5 -- and those digits appear in different places.
The 5 is in the ones place, the 7 is in the tens place, and the 2 is in the hundreds place. Let's think about those "places". Each "place" in a
number is a power of 10: 1 is 10^0, 10 is 10^1, 100 is 10^2.
The digits are there in those places to tell you how many copies of that power of 10 to use. So 275 uses 2 hundreds, 7 tens, and 5 ones.
We could write this by pulling apart the different places and writing
275 = 200 + 70 + 5 which is 2 * 10^2 + 7 * 10^1 + 5 * 10^0. So we
can write 275 as a sum of copies of powers of 10, and the digits we use tell us how many copies of each power of 10 to include.
To take another example, look at 17025. This has digits not only in the ones, tens, and hundreds places but also the thousands and
ten-thousands places. This can be written also as a sum of copies of powers of 10:
17025 = 1 * 10000 + 7 * 1000 + 0 * 100 + 2 * 10 + 5 * 1
or, 1 * 10^4 + 7 * 10^3 + 0 * 10^2 + 2 * 10^1 + 5 * 10^0.
What those very simple examples illustrate is the fact that **every nonnegative integer can be written as a sum of copies of powers of 10**
and the number of copies ranges from 0 to 9 (which are the digits of the number).
This format for writing numbers is called the base 10 or decimal representation of the number.
The word decimal doesn't mean fractions like 3.14. It uses the prefix "deci" which means 10. So the decimal representation of a number is
our usual way of writing things where the digits refer to copies of powers of 10, in different places.
Why do we use powers of 10? It's simply because we're human beings and we have ten fingers, and long ago this is how we learned to
count. If we'd evolved to have 8 fingers, or 16, then things would have turned out differently.
Humans like you and I store and process numbers in decimal form. All the arithmetic you learned when you were a kid, for example,
uses base 10 representation. Computers, on the other hand, are not human and do not have 10 fingers. Our use of base 10 representation
makes no sense to a computer, despite the fact that computers seem to have no trouble working with numbers. But in fact, below the
surface, in order to do any math on a computer --- and the only thing a computer actually does, is math --- we have to learn how to translate
from our world of numbers to theirs. How do we do that?
You have to understand that computers are electronic devices, so they only understand two things: On, and off. Computers process
electrical pulses that have only those two states. We usually represent those two states with either a 1 (for "on") or a 0 (for "off"). So
whereas we humans have literally ten digits on our hands and therefore ten digits used for numbers, computers only have two digits.
Since there are only two, we refer to this as binary rather than decimal, and the term binary digit is usually shortened to just "bit".
Everything you see a computer do, including the playback of this video, your word processor, the video game you like to play --- it's all just an
extremely long string of bits telling the hardware what to do. Any information processed by a computer is in binary, including
numbers. So how is this done when you only have two digits?
Just like we can write every number as a sum of copies of powers of 10, it turns out we can write any number as a sum of copies of powers
of 2. When we do this, we create what's called the base 2 or binary representation of that number. Because we're going to be using
powers of 2, here they are from 2^0 which is 1 all the way up through 2^11 which is 2048. Hard-core computer people might recognize
2^10 or 1024 because this is the number of bytes in a kilobyte. I highly recommend you learn these powers of 2 so that they are as
familiar to you as powers of 10. Look for example at 275 again. Although it's not
necessarily easy to see, we can write this number as a sum of powers of 2 like this:
275 = 256 + 16 + 2 + 1. All those are powers of 2 and there were
several that we skipped. In this representation we used
1 2^8
0 2^7
0 2^6
0 2^5
1 2^4
0 2^3
0 2^2
1 2^1
1 2^0
The binary representation of the number 275 is the string of digits you see in the second row: 100010011.
Notice importantly that *unlike* decimal representation where we use the digits 0 through 9, in binary the only digits we ever use
are 0 and 1. We'd never see a 2, or a 5 or a 7 show up because this would simply mean we'd use a higher power
of 2. It's just like how you don't see "13" show up as one of the digits in a decimal representation.
Here's another example of changing a decimal number to binary: 1902. That number can be written as this sum of powers of 2:
1902 = 1024 + 512 + 256 + 64 + 32 + 8 + 4 + 2 So we have 2^10, 2^9, 2^8, then a 2^6, 2^5,
2^3, 2^2, and 2^1 and no other powers of 2. That means the binary representation is 11101101110.
It's not totally clear right now how we can easily split up a number into a sum of powers of 2 like this other than through guess and check. But
don't worry -- In a later video we're going to present a speedy algorithm for doing this which will make it easy to convert representations
from base 10 to base 2. Notice that converting the representation in the
other direction, from binary to decimal, is on the other hand pretty easy. For example look at the binary integer 10101100. This is saying this
number 2^2 + 2^3 + 2^5 + 2^7 and a calculator will tell you this is the decimal number 172. Just use the bits to tell you which powers of 2 to
include, find those powers of 2, then sum them up.
So in this video you've learned what our primary school concept of base 10 representation means, what a binary digit or bit
is, what base 2 or binary representation means, a basic first idea of how to convert an integer from decimal to binary representation (although
we're going to improve on this in a later video) and how to convert from binary to decimal. That's a big step toward being able to
understand how computers and computer programs really work! Congratulations and see you in the next video.