In the previous video, you learned about decimal or base 10 representation of an integer which is how humans think about numbers, and
binary or base 2 representation which is how computers think about them. It turns out that binary isn't the *only* way computers represent
numbers, though. There are two other number bases that are commonly used, and in this video we're going to learn about those.
We saw in the last video that the usual base 10 or decimal representation is where you think of a number as a sum of copies of powers of 10.
We use 10 because most humans have 10 fingers. But what if you encountered an alien species with 8 fingers? They would probably
count the same way, but their system would involve representing a number using copies of powers of 8, and only the digits 0 through 7.
That's actually not science fiction, but a common way for computers to represent integers.
Just as it's possible to write any number as a sum of copies of powers of 2 or 10, we can write any number (remember this means
nonnegative integer for now) as a sum of copies of powers of 8. When we do this,
we are using the base 8 or octal representation of that number.
Here are the powers of 8 from 0 through 11, for reference. If some of of these look familiar, remember that 8 is a power of 2, and so all of
these are also powers of 2 which we saw last time.
In the last video we practiced with converting an integer from decimal to binary and vice versa. Let's do the same thing now, with octal.
Look at the integer 196. This is in decimal form --- it can't be in octal because the digit "9" does not exist in octal. We can write 196 as...
196 = 3 * 64 + 0 * 8 + 4 * 1
Remember we're using powers of 8 here, and because of that we can use digits 0 through 7, we're not restricted to just 0 or 1.
As with base 10 and base 2, writing 196 in base 8 means stripping off the digits and writing them in a string:
196 in base 10 = 304 in base 8
Notice we say "three zero four" not "three hundred and four" because the "3" here is *not* hundreds.
Likewise, let's say we have 1402 that's represented in base 8. What is this number in base 10? Just like with binary, converting from
octal to decimal is easy --- just count up the powers of 8.
1402 = 1 * 8^3 + 4 * 8*2 + 0 * 8^1 + 2 * 8^0 = 770.
Converting from binary to octal is easy too, in fact octal is often used to shorten binary strings.
Given the binary string, group the bits into threes and convert each group of three to a number between 0 and 7, and that's your octal
representation. For example, take the binary integer 10110001.
Group into threes: (010)(110)(001) Adding the zero on the left to pad it, so it's a group of 3.
Then convert each group to decimal which is easy because the numbers are small: 010 is 2, 110 is 6, 001 is 1.
The resulting octal integer is 261. (As a decimal, that's 177.)
Continuing this trend of using number bases that are powers of 2, another common base used in computer science is base 16, known as
hexadecimal. If you've been around computers you have probably seen hexadecimal numbers. They're sometimes used for example to
represent colors in web design --- for example this website lets you dial up a color using hexdecimal code.
They are also used in URL shortening services.
Hexadecimal or base 16 is the same idea as base 2, 8, or 10 --- except instead of writing an integer as a sum of copies of powers of 2, 8, or
10, we write it as a sum of copies of powers of 16. This introduces something curious.
In base 2, we used digits either 0 or 1 to represent the place values. And in octal we used 0 through 7.
In base 16, we'd use 0 through 15. But this would get confusing to use two decimal digits to represent a single place value,
so we use the ordinary 0 through 9 to represent 0 through 9, and for 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, and 15 we use the letters a, b, c, d, e, and f.
For example, the hexadecimal number "1A8" is
1A8 = 1 * 16^2 + (10) * 16^1 + 8 * 16^0 which is 424 in base 10.
Converting the other way, look at the decimal number 250. Written as a sum of powers of 16, this is
250 = 15 * 16^1 + 10 * 16^0. The "digit" 15 is represented be the letter F and 10 by A. So 250 in base 10 is "FA" in base 16.
Hexadecimal is widely used because it crunches the size of an integer down into a smaller string of digits. Notice the three-digit
decimal integer 250 is only two digits long in base 16. In binary the result is more dramatic. To convert from binary to hexadecimal, similarly
to how we converted binary to base 8, group the bits into fours and convert each group into 0-9 or A-F. For example
10110001 would be grouped as (1011)(0001) which would convert to (11)(1) or B1. Hexadecimal in other words represents a
binary integer in one-fourth of its original length, which saves on storage.
Finally here's a dad joke for you. Why did the computer scientist always get Christmas and Halloween mixed up?
It's because Oct 31 = Dec 25.
[sigh] OK, so in this video we learned about octal or
base 8 representation, hexadecimal or base 16 representation, and how to convert back and forth between base 2, 8, 10, and 16. Next up
we're going to address a missing piece, which is an algorithm to quickly convert from decimal to any of these other bases. See you there.