So far we've learned about representing integers in different number bases, specifically base 10 which is what we learn as kids, and
bases 2, 8, and 16 which are commonly used in computer science. These different number bases are a lot like different units of
measurement. Milliliters, gallons, and cups are all measures of volume, but each one is more useful in some contexts than others, and we
often have to convert from one measure of volume to another. Similarly, it's important to be able to convert between different number base
representations. We've seen how to convert a representation from base 2, 8, or 16 to base 10 (which is pretty simple) and from base 2 to
either base 8 or 16 (which is also pretty simple). Going from base 10 to any other base, on the other hand, isn't hard but when we did it,
it might have felt to you like guesswork. In this video we're going to make the process of converting from decimal to other bases more
foolproof through a simple and rigorous algorithm.
First of all, an "algorithm" is a finite process or a set of rules that we or a computer will follow to make a computation or solve a problem. An
algorithm, if correct, will have a definite start point, and it will end after a finite number of steps with a correct result.
For example, in school we learned algorithms for multiplying two numbers together. In computer science we have algorithms for all
kinds of things like sorting of lists, finding the shortest path through a network, and more. Algorithms are at the core of computer science
and you will be visiting them regularly throughout this course and throughout your careers.
We're going to describe an algorithm now that will convert a number from base 10 to base 2, and to set the stage, let's consider the following
process that isn't really useful by itself but illustrates the main idea.
Take the number 2417 in base 10. Starting with this input, let's go through some steps.
First, divide 2417 by 10 and record the quotient (how many times 10 goes into it) and the remainder (the amount left over). If you do the
long division on this (another algorithm we learned in school), 10 goes into 2417 241 times with a remainder of 7. So the quotient is 241
and the remainder is 7. Note that the remainder must be less than 10, because we're dividing by 10, and if the remainder were 10 or greater
we could just divide again. Record both the quotient and the remainder.
Now repeat this process but use the quotient from the previous step, 241, as the new input. Divide 241 by 10: The quotient is 24 and the
remainder is 1. Record both. Now repeat the process again using the previous step's quotient as the new input: Divide 24 by 10 and
you have a new quotient of 2 and a remainder of 4. Repeat again: Divide 2 by 10 and this yields a quotient of 0 and a remainder of 2. If
we were to repeat this process more, we would be getting a quotient and a remainder of 0,
so once we get a quotient of 0 the algorithm terminates.
Now if you look at the list of remainders we kept, these are the base 10 digits of the original number 2417 in reverse order. Repeated
division by 10 in other words produces a list of the digits.
I want you to notice two things at this point. First, algorithms in computer science and in real life often work by repetition ---
you have just few lines, or even one line of code that performs a simple operation and the algorithm simply repeats, or iterates, over these
instructions until some kind of condition is met and then it stops. Remember that concept as we explore algorithms in the future.
Second, let's be honest, this algorithm on its own is totally useless because we don't need to go through all these steps to see the digits of a
decimal number, we just look at it. The power of the algorithm really comes from the fact that we can modify it to do other things.
In fact, this very algorithm can be modified just slightly to give us the BINARY digits of this same number. All we have to do is change the
instruction of dividing by 10, to dividing by 2. When we divide an integer by 2, we always get a remainder of either 0 (if the number is even)
or 1 (if it's odd) and never anything else. So those remainders are going to be bits and those bits are the digits of the binary form of
the integer we start with.  Let's see how this works with a simple two-digit
decimal integer, 37. Again, the way the conversion algorithm works is that we will repeatedly divide the input by 2, record the
quotient and remainder, and then repeat that process using the previous step's quotient as the new input, and then stop when the
quotient is 0. So first, 37 / 2 is 18 with a remainder of 1.
Record 18 and 1 in memory.
Next: 18 / 2 is 9 with remainder 0. Record those two in memory.
Next: 9 / 2 is 4 with remainder 1.
Next: 4 / 2 is 2 with remainder 0.
Next: 2  / 2 is 1 with remainder 0.
Next: 1 / 2 gives a quotient of 0 with a remainder of 1, so record those in memory but then stop since the quotient is 0.
To end the algorithm and get the binary representation, construct a string from the remainders in the reverse order in which they
appeared: 100101. Let's check to make sure this is right. 100101 is
1 2^5, 1 2^2, and 1 2^0 which is 32 + 4 + 1 and that is indeed 37 in base 10.
Now you try it. In the very first video, we converted the base 10 integer 275 to binary without this algorithm and the answer was
100010011. Pause the video, and take a few minutes to work through the algorithm to convert the bases with the algorithm.
Here's the work for this process, and you can see that it does indeed produce the right binary.
And that's an algorithm for converting a number from decimal to binary. But --- you wouldn't be wrong to have a LOT of questions about this
algorithm. For example, WHY does this algorithm produce the correct binary form of the integer? Are we sure that it always does
produce the correct binary, or did we just get lucky with these two examples? Are we sure that the algorithm always terminates, or is it
possible that we could start with an integer that throws the algorithm into an infinite loop?
These are questions that, as computer scientists, we have to ask and answer about every algorithm we meet. It's not enough just to
be able to write code and compute answers --- kids, or AIs, can do that. What we have to be able to do is reason about algorithms like this
and explain why they work, in ALL cases and not just the ones we choose or observe. A million examples will not do this for us. We
need to use mathematics, and mathematical reasoning, to get into the deep machinery of computing processes to help us understand
things that simply writing code cannot explain. Being able to use mathematics to go beyond code, and reason about computational
processes, is a major high-level learning goal for this course and we will be revisiting it repeatedly throughout everything we do.
For now, we are going to take it on faith that this base conversion algorithm really works. But we will need to come back to this algorithm
later, once we have more tools for thinking about algorithms, and think about why it works.
Notice that this algorithm, while a little tedious to do by hand, is quite fast because every iteration of the loop where we divide and record
the quotient and remainder literally cuts the new input size in half. This means that it will scale up well --- while it obviously takes more
steps to convert a large integer than it does a small one, a number with twice as many decimal digits does not necessarily take twice
as many steps. Another important concept we will be thinking about in this course is just how exactly algorithms scale up when the input size
increases and how that scaling up might be modeled with mathematical functions.
Another great thing about this algorithm is that it can be modified to convert a decimal integer into ANY base, not just binary, simply by
changing the number we divide by. For example if we wanted to convert the number 1982 from decimal to octal, just run the same
process but divide by 8. In this case,
1982 / 8 = 247 with remainder 6
247 / 8 = 30 with remainder 7
30 / 8 = 3 with remainder 6
3 / 8 = 0 with remainder 3, stop here and list back the remainders in reverse order to get 3676 which is 1982 in octal.
Here's an example in hexadecimal that shows how fast this can be --- look at 161067 in base 10.
161067 / 16 = 10066 with remainder 11
10066 / 16 = 629 with remainder 2
629 / 16 = 39 with remainder 5
39 // 16 = 2 with remainder 7
2 // 16 = 0 with remainder 2
So the base 16 representation of 161067 is 2752B (remember B is the hexadecimal for the number 11). Again we have not attempted to
explain WHY this works other than by analogy when we divide by 10. To prove that the algorithm works for any base will require some
mathematical tools we will be encountering in later videos.
In this video, you learned an algorithm for converting from base 10 to any other base you want. And we've introduced some important
concepts about algorithms -- what they are, the importance of reasoning through them, and the concept of understanding mathematically how
they scale up. In the next few videos we're going to focus on binary representation specifically and think about how computers do
basic arithmetic with base 2.