As we've learned, binary or base 2 representation is how computers store and process numerical information. In fact it's how
computers store and process ANY kind of information, since computers don't know how to do anything else besides math. Everything you
do on a computer is the result of some mathematical processes performed on numbers written in binary.
In the next few videos we're going to learn how this works on the most basic level --- specifically by learning how to do arithmetic -
basic addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division - using numbers represented in binary.
This video focuses on addition, and then there will be videos for the other three basic arithmetic operations.
To understand how to add two binary numbers together, let's first do some VERY basic review about how we learned to add two decimal
numbers together back when we were kids. Look at the sum 147 + 782.
The algorithm we learned back in the day goes like this. First write the numbers vertically like so. THen start adding in the ones place.
Here, 7 + 2 is 9 so that goes in the ones place for the answer. Then move on to the tens place. This time, the sum of the digits, 4 + 8, is
12. It doesn't make sense to write a "12" in the answer for the tens place because 12 is bigger than 10. It overflows the space. So what we do
is write down the 2 (which is in the ones place of this digit sum) and "carry the 1" over to the hundreds place, where we now have three
things to add: the 1 and the 7, and the additional 1 from the carry. That adds up to 9, and this doesn't overflow the space so we write
it down. Therefore the answer is 929.
So in base 10, all addition is really carried out only on single digit numbers, 0 through 9, one place at a time. If we do a digit sum and it gives
a result bigger than 9, then we split off the ones digits from the tens digit and carry that tens digit up to the next place, and continue until
there is no more carrying and no more digits.
Adding numbers in binary uses the same principle and in some ways it's easier, because you now only have two possible digits to work
with --- 0 and 1 --- rather than ten of them. Since, as we just pointed out, addition of larger numbers is really just repeated addition of
single-digit numbers together with this "Carrying" process, let's think about what happens when we add two single bits together.
Well, 0 in binary still means 0, so 0 + 0 = 0. And 1 still means 1, so 1 + 0 = 1 and also 0 + 1 = 1 because addition is commutative, meaning the
order of addition doesn't affect the answer. But when we add 1 and 1, it gets a little tricky. The answer of course is 2, but remember we are in
binary now, so: 1 + 1 = 10 which is 2 in binary. That means when we add 1 and 1, we end up with a two digit number that overflows the
space. It's analogous to when we added 8 and 4 in the starting example. We got 12, so we wrote down 2 and carried the 1. Similarly, any
time we add 1 + 1 in binary, we will have to carry a 1.
Now we're ready to think about how computers add larger numbers in binary. Let's look at 110 + 11. In decimal, this is 6 + 3 so the answer
should be 9. But we want to do this entirely in binary without changing the representation to decimal,
because computers wouldn't make that change.
Just like in base 10, line these up vertically like so. I added a 0 on the left side of the second number just for padding, to show you how the
two numbers line up. It's not really necessary.
Now just like in base 10, add one place at a time starting with the ones place. Here, 0 + 1 is just 1, so that goes in the ones place for the
answer. Moving to the next place (which is the "2" place, not the "tens" place) we encounter 1 + 1. As we saw above, the answer is not "2" but
10. This overflows the space, so we will write down 0 and carry the 1.
Now in the next place we have 1 + 1 + 0. Just like in decimal, we can only really add two things at a time, and the grouping doesn't
matter because addition is not only commutative but also associative. So add 1+1 to get 10, then add 0 to just get 10 again.
Just as in the last step, this overflows the one-digit sized space allowed for the answer, so just put down the ones place and carry the 1 over.
In that next place over, there's nothing --- you can think of it as two zeroes if you want, so we'd be adding 1 + 0 + 0 which is just 1, and
that goes here. So in the end we have as the result 1001, and
in decimal that is indeed 9 like it's supposed to be.
Let's look at another example: 11101 + 11001.  In decimal this is 29 + 25 so the answer is supposed to be 54. I encourage you to pause
the video and try working this out for yourself before watching the solution, and remember it is totally fine to make mistakes! You won't really
learn anything otherwise, and nobody is watching.
So we begin by lining these up vertically and adding place by place starting with the ones place. This is 1 + 1 which is 10. Write 0 and
carry the 1. In the 2's place, we have 1 + 0 + 0 which is just a 1, so write that. there's no carry here, so just move to the 4's place.
This is 1 + 0 which is just a 1, so write that with no carry. then in the 8's place, we have 1+1 again, so write 0 and carry the 1. Now in the
16's place, we have 1 + 1 + 1. This is technically 3, but in binary that's 11. This is pretty much the same situation as having 10 ---
the 11 overflows the single digit space, so we copy down the first 1 and carry the second. That last place there has nothing in it, but you
can think of it as two zeroes. 1 + 0 + 0 is 1, and so that's the last part of the result.
We arrive at the answer 110110, and if you check it, this is indeed 54 in base 10.
So congratulations, you've now learned the basics behind doing addition in binary without translating to decimal first! Now we have to
tackle subtraction, which will happen in the next video.