In the last video we learned how to do addition in binary. Next up is subtraction. Since it was helpful to first think carefully about how addition
worked in base 10 arithmetic, let's begin with a look at how subtraction works in base 10.
Here's an example: 326 - 152. The way we learned it when we were kids is first, just as with addition, write these on top of each other
with the larger number at the top. Then go place by place and subtract only the numbers in each place. In this example the first step
is 6 - 2 which is 4, and that goes in the ones place for the answer. But when we move on to the tens place, we have to think about what to
do. We have 2 - 5, but this is a negative number, and it doesn't make sense to put -3 in the tens place. So what we do is sort of the
opposite of "carrying" in addition --- we "borrow". We borrow a 1 from the next place up and make that 2 into a 12.
Now the subtraction makes sense: 12 - 5 is 7, so we put that down in the tens place.
The final place used to be 3 - 1 but now it's 2 - 1 since we borrowed so the final answer is 174.
What exactly is going on with "borrowing"? A lot of kids struggle with that concept and it's no wonder. It feels like an arbitrary rule but there's
actually a basis to it. In addition we sometimes have to "carry", when for example we added 4 + 8 in the tens place and we end up with a
number that's too large. We add two single digits and get something too big for a single digit, so we split it up --- the 12 becomes 10 + 2
and we add 1 to the next place value up. Borrowing is just this in reverse --- if the subtraction on a single digit results in
something too small, we grab one copy of the next place value up and combine it with the current place.
We say that we're borrowing a 1, but actually it's a 10 because it's one copy of the next higher place value.
That 1 is ten times the size of the digits in the current place.
Subtraction in binary follows the same rules as subtraction in decimal, but the concept of place value is based on 2s rather than 10s.
Let's see how this works with the example 1101 - 110. In decimal this would be 13 minus 6, so the answer should be 7.
Lining these up with the larger one on top, in the ones place we have 1 - 0. this is just 1, so put that down with no extra steps needed.
In the 2's place we have something to think about. 0 - 1 is analogous to having 2 - 5 in the earlier base 10 example. It doesn't make sense
to put a negative number in this place in the result (and anyway we haven't defined what it means for a bit to be negative at all yet). So, to
follow the same rules, here we are going to borrow from the next place up.
But it's a little tricky. Borrowing reduces the 1 that's in the 8's place to a 0. And although it says "1", it's from the next place up --- so it's
actually a 2, because the next place up is twice the size of the current place. In base 10 it was ten times the size, but we are in base 2.
So again borrowing a 1 from here is going to put a 2, not a 10, here. Since a 2 goes here and we're in binary, we will write "10" but that's
not ten, that's just the binary for 2. So in our example, we have 10 minus 1, which is really 2 - 1 so the answer is just 1.
Moving to the 4's place, we have 0 - 1 which is the same situation as previously. So borrow a 1 from the 8s place, turn that 0 into a 10, and
subtract to get 1. There's nothing left, so the answer is 111. In decimal, that's "7" which is what we were supposed to get.
That's tricky, so let's recap. Just as in regular base 10 subtraction, binary subtraction goes one place at a time. If the single bit subtraction
can be carried out normally --- if it's 0 - 0, 1-0, or 1-1 -- then do so. Otherwise, if we have a 0 - 1, we borrow from the next place value up.
Borrowing a 1 from the next place value up is actually borrowing a 2, or a 10 -- just as in decimal, borrowing a 1 from the next place
value up is actually borrowing a 10. Now we can subtract. Continue this process until we reach the end of the digits.
Let's do a more complex example: 100101 minus 11111. In decimal this is 37 - 31
so the answer is supposed to be 6. Let's go through the process.
Starting with the 1's digit, it's just 1-1 which is 0, and no borrowing is necessary. Moving to the 2's place, we have 0 - 1. Like we said, we need
to borrow a 1 from the next place up. So this 1 that's in the 4's place becomes a 0, and it's a 2 or 10 here in this place.
Now 10 minus 1 is 1 and we're done with the 2's place, so move to the 4's place. Because we borrowed, the 4s place now has 0 - 1 so
here we are again. What we should do is borrow a 1 from the next place up, but there's nothing there! It says 0. So we have to keep
looking in this top number and move up the place values until we can find some place from which we can borrow. The 16's place is also a
0. We don't encounter a 1 until the 32's place. So there's a chain reaction here: Borrow a 1 from the 32's place to have a 10 in the 16's
place. But we also have to borrow a 1 from the 16s place to give a 10 to the 8's place. This reduces the 10 to just a 1 in the 16s place and
adds 10 in the 8's place. But then borrow from THAT to give a 10 to the 4s place like we originally needed, so the 8s place is now a 1
and the 4s place is now a 10. Subtraction can proceed as usual in the 4s place, since 10 minus 1 is 1. Now move to the 8s place -- we
have 1 minus 1 which is 0 without borrowing. The 16s place is the same.
And the 32s place is now entirely zero, so there's nothing to do there.
We end with the number 110. That's a 6 in decimal, and remember that's what the answer was supposed to be.
This example was quite tricky because we had to borrow from multiple places before subtraction could take place. This happens in
decimal subtraction too, and it's just as tricky -- like when we have 3104 minus 731. In this problem. the ones digit is no problem, but in
the tens digit we need to borrow a 1 from the hundreds place, but then we have to borrow another 1 from the
thousands place to be able to give to the hundreds place.
So in this video you have extended your skill set to include subtracting binary numbers and not just adding them.
That was tricky! So well done. Next up is multiplication.