By now, I hope what you are seeing is that arithmetic in binary works pretty much exactly the same as it does in decimal, but the concept
of place value is changed, and understanding binary arithmetic requires a solid understanding of what place value means. As we move from
addition and subtraction to multiplication in this video and then division in the next, that theme will continue. As with addition and subtraction,
let's revisit the method for multiplying two integers in base 10 and keep a careful eye on place value.
So look at 263 times 13. Our school algorithm works like this. First position the numbers vertically with the larger one on top. Then
proceed to multiply the first number by the ones digit in the second. 3 times 3 is 9. 3 times 6 is 18, and just as in addition that overflows the
one-digit space allocated to it, so we write 8 and carry the 1. Now remember that *says* 1, but it's actually a ten because it's the tens digit
of 18, and we are going up a place, and every place is ten times larger than the previous place. We carry the 1, then multiply 3 times 2
and *add* the 1 (because that's what carrying is, just adding) to get 7.
Now we move on to the tens digit in the second number and we're going to store the result in a second row down below. Since this is the tens
digit, not the ones digit, we shift everything in that second register over by one unit because the result will start in the tens digit of the
answer. In this case the rest is easy because we're multiplying by 1, so we get 263. Then there's a final stage where we add both lower
rows, and just as before we sometimes have to carry a digit when adding. Our final answer is 3419.
Now, how would this work in binary? Let's start simple with 111 times 11. Let's roll with this and just try to follow the same rules as with base 10
multiplication. Well, 111 times 1 is just 111. Then in the second step, it's still 111 times 1 and that is still 111. But when we write it, we're
shifting over a unit because we're multiplying by a higher place value, just like we were at this stage of the base 10 multiplication. So you
can see that on one level, binary multiplication is shockingly easy because we are only ever multiplying by 1 which means just copy the
number down, or by 0 which makes everything zero.
So now we are just left with an addition problem, which we saw how to do two videos ago. We have 1 + 0 (although we don't write
the 0) which is 1. Then 1+1 which is 2, or 10, so put down 0 and carry the 1. Now we have 1+1+1 which is 3 or "11", so put down 1 and
carry the other 1. then we have 1+1, which is 10. 10101 is our result and in base 10 that's 16+4+1 which is 21,
which is good because the original numbers we multiplied are 7 and 3 in base 10.
So in fact the only thing really hard about binary multiplication is binary addition at the end.
Let's try a larger example, 11111 times 101. In base 10 that's 31 and 5, so the answer should be 155. Lining these up, we first multiply by 1
to get 11111. Then shift once, and multiply by 0. Then we need to shift another time since we are now two places higher. Multiply by 1 to get
11111. Now add these together: 1+0 is 1, 1+0 is 1, 1+1 is 0 carry the 1; 1+1+1 is 1 carry the 1, and this happens twice; 1+1 is 0 carry a 1, then
finally 10. That gives us 10011011 which you can check is indeed 155.
One more example will illustrate what happens when the addition at the end starts to stack up. Look at 11111 times 111. That's 31 again but
this time it's times 7. The answer should be 217. The multiplication steps are very simple and here's where it leads. Now we have to add --
but there's something new. We've never tried adding a stack of binary integers like this. In decimal, adding a stack of 3 or more integers
works pretty much the same as adding just two integers together, although when we do, the numbers can get quite large --- adding two
integers together in base 10, we sometimes don't carry just a 1 but for example in this case a 2.
We could handle adding a stack of binary integers in one of two ways. We could add just the first two levels then add the result to the
third level. That would work, but it seems like more work than needed. So let's try to adapt the base 10 method of adding to binary.
In the ones place, it's just 1 plus two zeroes that we don't write, so we have 1. In the 2s place we have 1 + 1 which is 0, carry the 1.
Now let's think. In the 4s place we have 1+1+1+1. This is 4. In binary, this is 100. What this means is that we have 0 here, and we need to
carry a 1 to TWO places up. It's like if we added a stack of decimal integers so high that the tens place added up to 106, we'd put down
6 and carry the 1, but not to the next place up but the place AFTER THAT since that 1 is one hundred, not ten. So we'll carry that 1 to the
16s place and leave it until we get there. But next we need to add the 8s place. This is 1+1+1 which is 11, so write 1 and carry the 1 also
to the 16s place. In that 16s place now we have 5 1's. That adds up to 5 which in binary is 101. So write 1 and carry the leftmost 1 up two
places. Moving on to the 64s place, we have 1+1 which is 0, carry the 1. So finally, we have in the 128s place 1+1+1 which is 11. The result is
11011001. Is it right? Let's convert to base 10: We get 217, which is indeed what we were supposed to get.
Whew! You've learned at least a couple of things in this video, first the general process of multiplying in binary. And second, possibly
more importantly, you've learned that place value is really what all of arithmetic hinges on. If you can understand what all the digits of a
number mean in terms of their place value, this unlocks all of arithmetic and also a real understanding of how a machine can do
arithmetic. Next up we will tackle our fourth and final arithmetic operation, division in binary.