In the last few videos, we've been focusing on integers in binary. For this video, though, we're switching focus back to decimal to try to
understand more about division. Let's start with a simple question. At the time I am making this video, it's 10 o'clock in the morning. What time
will it be 100 hours from now? Pause the video and see if you can answer that question. If you can't figure it out, that's OK, just give it a try
and see what kind of tricks or methods you come up with.
Here's one way to think about this question. 24 hours from now, it will be 10:00 am again, and so every time 24 hours passes the time on the
clock is the same. How many 24-hour increments happen in the space of 100 hours? One day is 24 hours; two is 48; three is 72; and
four would be 96. If I went forward one more day this would be over 100 hours, so stop. 100 hours is four full days plus 4 extra hours. It's
really only the 4 extra hours that matters here. In 96 hours it will still be 10:00am; in 100 hours it'll be four hours after that, or 2pm.
What does this have to do with division you ask? Well, when we divide one integer into another, we're not performing a mysterious
algorithm --- we're actually doing something very simple that kids do all the time. Look for example at the problem 22 divided by 3. What
this is asking is really: **How many groups of 3 can I make out of 22 things, and how many of those things would be left out of a group?** In
this case, you can take 22 items and group them into 7 clusters of 3, and there would be 1 left over. So we say that 3 "goes into" 22 7
times
with a "Remainder" of 1. The quotient 7 is the number of groups; the 1 is the number of items that don't go into a group.
So when we asked what time it would be 100 hours from now, we thought about it by asking, how many groups of 24 hours can we make out
of 100, and how many hours would be left over? The answer was that we can make 4 groups, and 4 hours are left over. In other
words we solved the problem by simply dividing 100 by 24 and focusing on the remainder.
Notice that division, in this way of thinking about it, is really not a separate operation at all, but just a combination of multiplication and
addition. When we divide one number by another, we ask ourselves how many times, literally "times", we need to cluster and then
add on the leftovers. And notice that the leftover has to be smaller by the thing we are dividing by --- if it were larger, then we could
just form another group.
The exact way of expressing this idea that division is just multiplication and addition put together, is in a mathematical fact known as the
Division Algorithm. It states:
Given any two integers a and b with a nonzero, there exist unique integers q and r such that b = aq + r,
and r satisfies the inequality 0 is less than or equal to r which is less than a.
We can see this in the examples we did above. This way of thinking about division is extremely powerful especially in computer science, since
it means that division doesn't require new operations --- just multiplication and addition which computers are very good at doing.
There's some mathematical language in the Division Algorithm that needs unpacking. First of all notice that like an algorithm there is input ---
two integers which we call a and b and we stipulate that a doesn't equal 0. Then there is output -- two integers we call q and r. Here "q"
stands for quotient and "r" means remainder. The Division Algorithm states three facts about q and r. First it says they exist; regardless of
the integers, as long as we aren't dividing by 0 there will always be a quotient and a remainder. This is like the requirement of any
algorithm that as long as the input is valid, the algorithm should produce a valid result. Then it says that the quotient and remainder are
unique --- meaning that there's only one pair that will result from the division process. It wouldn't be a very good algorithm if one set of
inputs produced one set of outputs one time and another a different time. Then finally, it places a size restriction on the remainder --- it
could be as small as 0 but must be less than the thing we divide by.
Let's actually think about why the Division Algorithm works. Let's say that b is bigger than a, so we have a bunch of things whose precise
number is "b" that we want to package into groups of size "a". Let q be the number of groups and r the number of items left
unpackaged. Start a process with q = 1. This packages up a of the items, but there are a lot left over. In fact there are b - a of the items left
over. So increment q to 2, which leaves b - 2a left over and notice that b - 2a, while still nonnegative, is less than b - a because you are
subtracting a larger amount from b. Every time you make a new package you increase q by 1, and you are removing "a" of the items, which
decreases r while still keeping it nonnegative. Since the sequence of "r" values is strictly decreasing and consists only of nonnegative
numbers, at some point, you are going to reach a point where you cannot package up any more of the items because the r is as small as
it can get. In other words we know that regardless of what we start with, as long as a is not 0, this algorithm will always terminate.
When it does, notice you have r = b - aq, which in other words is b = aq + r and r satisfies the inequality 0 <= r < a because if r were bigger
than a, we would just make another package. The q is our quotient and r is the remainder.
We'll skip explaining why these two numbers are "unique" but you're encouraged to think about what would happen if you had two
different values of q and two different values of r that produced the same packaging that the algorithm does.
So what the Division Algorithm says basically is that integer division is more or less just repeated subtraction. We start with a number
we are dividing and a number we are dividing by, and start subtracting off the second number over and over until we can't do it anymore
without entering negative territory. And that's why long division works! When we do long division, all we are doing is subtraction in
chunks --- first seeing how many times we can subtract off from the largest place, then subtracting that off and seeing how many times
we can subtract off from the next largest place, and so on until no more subtraction can be done.
So the Division Algorithm is a mathematically precise way to express how we do long division, without actually doing any long
division. There's an important application here as well to an operation that is critical for modern computer applications as well. That
operation is called the **modulus*** operation. You probably didn't learn this in school, but it's both simple and very useful. We often use the
percent symbol `%` to denote it. Here's how it works:
Given two integers `a` and `b` with a not equal to 0,  `b % a` which we read "b mod a" is the remainder that is left when you divide b by a.
For example: 37 % 10 is 7, because 37 divided by 10 is 3 with remainder 7.
And 100 % 24 is 4, because as we saw earlier
24 goes into 100 4 times with a remainder of 4.
Similarly 22 % 3 is 1 because 3 goes into 22 7 times with remainder 1.
One technical note at this point: The way we are defining the modulus operator here, as the remainder that's left over after division, only
makes sense if neither a nor b are negative. If one of these is negative, long division isn't defined in the same way as when they are
positive. This is a glitch in our definition of the modulus operator that we will fix later. We're going to keep it simple for now though and go
on working with just positive numbers, although we don't exclude the b from being zero.
The modulus operator has thousands of uses, including date and time calculations like we started this video with, and for example is a
central tool in cryptographic methods that secure your data.
So in this video you learned that division can be thought of as repeated subtraction, and this notion culminates in the Division Algorithm, and
you also learned about the modulus operator and how it works. There's just one video left in this module, and that brings us back to binary
to think about how negative numbers are represented.