In this video we're returning to binary, to cover a loose end that we haven't discussed. That's the question of how to represent negative
numbers. All the integers we've worked with so far have been zero or positive.
Can you even represent a negative number in binary? If so, how?
Let's think how we might approach that problem, with an example. We know that the decimal integer 9 is represented 1001 in binary.
How might we represent -9? We can't just stick a minus sign onto 1001 because computers won't know what to do with it --- they only
recognize 0 and 1 and no other symbols. One approach would be to change the way we do binary representation in the first place by
adding a bit onto the end of every number that holds information about its sign. For example we could take 1001 and make it 01001 if we
mean positive 9 and 11001 if we mean negative 9. That would certainly distinguish 9 from -9. But first of all it would make -9
indistinguishable from 25 in binary, and even worse, it would mess up the way we do arithmetic, because if we added these two
together we should get 0, but instead we get this, which is definitely NOT zero.
So we'd have to completely redo all the algorithms for arithmetic, which seems like a lot of work.
But it's not a terrible idea to add a bit to a number to indicate its sign. We just need to do it in a way that makes it workable with all the
arithmetic we've seen. It turns out there are multiple ways to do this in computer science,
but the most common one is called "two's complement".
Here's the process for how to write a negative integer in binary using two's complement. To begin, we first have to predefine the number of
bits used to represent any integer. This is built into the hardware choices of computers, for example when you hear of a "64-bit" or "32-bit"
operating system, it means that the system is designed to handle chunks of data of that size --- 64 bits at a time or 32 bits at a time.
In an 8-bit system, information would be handled 8 bits at a time, so in that case the number 9 would not be 1001 but 0000 1001.
The largest number an 8 bit system could handle is 1111 1111 which is 255 in decimal.
Once we know the number of bits used to represent an integer, here's how to represent a negative number using two's complement.
Start with the positive version of that number. For example we saw 9 is 0000 1001. Then first invert or flip all the bits, from 0 to 1 and 1 to 0.
Then add 1 to this. The result is the two's complement binary representation of the number.
For example we saw +9 is 0000 1001. To represent -9, first flip the bits to 1111 0110. Then add 1 to get 1111 0111. That's -9.
Notice that when we add these two, we do not actually get 0 like you might expect. Instead we get 2^9. But since we are in an 8-bit system,
this truncates to 0. Thanks to the 8-bit system therefore we end up with 0, as we should.
This makes two's complement consistent with the rules of addition we already have.
You do the next example first, using the 8-bit integer 199. In binary this is 1100 0110. Follow the steps to write -199 in two's complement
form. Pause the video and work that out, and again don't worry about mistakes.
So to get -199, first flip the bits on 199 to get 0011 1001. Then add 1: 0011 1010. That's -198. You can check if you want by adding
these two binaries together, and you'll see that you again get 2^9, which in an 8-bit system is 0, which is what you are supposed to get.
Why is this method is called "two's complement"? Well, the "two" comes from the fact that we are in base 2. THe "complement"
comes from the bit flipping. As we'll explore in a later module on logic, flipping bits like this is akin to changing from off to on or vice versa, or
more accurately it's like changing from "true" to "false" or vice versa. The opposite of a truth value is called its "complement" in mathematics
and that's the first step in the process. And as the examples we saw hint at, when we add a number x to its opposite -x, we'll get 2^(n+1)
if we are in an n-bit system, so the x and -x are "complementary" in that sense.
In this video you learned how to represent negative inegers using two's complement, which is a way of writing negative numbers that
works with the binary arithmetic we've seen throughout this module. That's the end of this module on integer representation, so
congratulations! Next we'll explore the world of logic and see how computers use logic to operate.