The last video introduced the idea of quantification, which is what happens when we take a predicate, whose truth value can't be
determined because of a variable, and then making a claim about whether that predicate is *always* true or *sometimes* true. Since
quantified predicates are propositions, we can negate them. And in this video we're going to see how this is done.
Take a look at the universally quantified predicates from the last video that were false. How did we know they were false? For
example, why was "for all strings x, the length of x is positive" false? It was because we found a single example of a string that showed us
that *not all* strings have a positive length. That's called a *counterexample* --- an example that proves a universally quantified
statement is false. Universally quantified statements can be shown to be false by producing just one counterexample.
We can phrase this fact using negations. If you take the universally quantified statement "for all x, P(x)" and negate it, it is a claim that P(x) is
not universally true, or not *always* true. What does it mean when a statement is not always true? It *doesn't* mean that the statement is
always false. For example the statement "All cars are red" is not  true. But this doesn't mean that *no* cars are red --- that no red cars exist.
It just means that not all cars are red, or that there are cars that exist and are not red.
So a when a univerally quantified statement, something of the form "for all x, P(x) is true" is negated, we are saying that P(x) is
*sometimes* false. Or put differently, there exists an x that makes negation of P(x) true. We can put that in notation by saying: The
negation of "for all x, P(x)" is "there exists an x such that 'not P(x)'". So the negation of a universally quantified predicate is the
existential quantification of the negation of the predicate.
Likewise, look at the existentially quantified predicates that are false, like the one you did in the last video, S(x) is the absolute value of x is
negative. If we existentially quantify that predicate to get "there exists an x such that the absolute value of x is negative", that's a false
statement because we know from basic math than the absolute value of x is never negative --- that is, the absolute value of x is always zero
or positive. This sounds like a universal statement, doesn't it? In fact, what we see from this example is that the negation of "there
exists an x such that P(x)" is "for all x, not P(x)". So negating an existentially quantified statement gives a universally quantified
statement.
Here's one more example to put it all together. Look at the predicate C(x) where the domain is the set of all countries on Earth, and C(x) says
"the first letter of x is B". Pause the video while you do the following: First, write out in English or whatever language you prefer what the
statements "for all x C(x)" and "there exists an x such that C(x)" would say in plain language. Then, determine whether those statements are
true, or false. Then, write out their negations in plain language and determine whether those are true or false. Come on back here when you
are ready.
The universally quantified statement would say that Every country begins with the letter B. The existentially quantified statement would say that
At least one country begins with the letter B. There are other possible ways to say either of these. But when you put it this way, it's clear
that "For all x C(x)" is false, again because there are lots of counterexamples possible, for example France. And "There exists x such that
C(x)" is true, because there do exist countries beginning with a B, like Belize or Belarus.
The negation of "for all x C(x)" would be "There exists x such that not C(x)" which in plainer language would be "There exists a country
whose name doesn't begin with a B". And that's certainly true, in fact this statement is just saying that it's possible to find a
counterexample to the original universal statement. The negation of "there exists an x such that C(x)" is the universal statement "for
all x, not C(x)" or in other words, For every on Earth, the name of the country does not begin with a B. That is a false statement, and we
know it because that's a universal statement but there's a counterexample -- Belize, or Belarus. This makes sense because the
negation of a proposition should have the opposite truth value. The universal statement was false so its negation should be true, and
the existential statement was true so its negation should be false.
You've learned in this video that the negation of a universally quantified statement is an existentially quantified statement using the
negation of the original predicate. And likewise, the negation of an existentially quantified statement is a universally quantified statement
using the negation of the original predicate. There's just one more topic to touch on here, and that's how quantification works when you
have more than one variable. So stick around.