You've done a lot of work so far with predicates. You've learned what they are and how they related to propositions, how to
quantify them, how to negate them, and more! Great job so far. But there's one question left to think about -- what happens when your
predicate has more than just one variable?
Let's let P(x,y) is the statement x*y is bigger than or equal to 0. To determine the truth value of this, we need the values of not just one but
two inputs. For example P(2,3) is true and P(2,-4) is false. We saw in the last two videos that quantifying the variable turns a predicate
into a proposition with a definite truth value. Does that work for two-variable predicates?
Let's suppose we took P(x,y) and quantified the variable x by saying "for all x, P(x,y) is true". Unlike earlier, this is still an underdetermined
statement because we've quantified the x variable but the y variable is still unknown. Quantifying the x variable turns a two-variable
predicate with variables x,y into a one-variable predicate with variable y. It's still a predicate and unless we do something with the y variable
too, we still can't determine its truth value. The general principle here is that for two variable predicates, *both* variables must be quantified
before we can say anything definite about truth values.
Let's keep the universal quantifier here on x. There are two ways to quantify the missing variable y --- universal or existential. If we
universally quantify y, we would have this in notation --- for all x and for all y, P(x,y) is true. In plain language this would say that x*y is
positive for every possible pair of inputs x and y. Now this statement has a definite truth value, namely FALSE because I can find a
counterexample easily, for instance x = 2 and y = -4. So it's not the case that P(x,y) is true "for all" values of x and y.
But we could also have existentially quantified y, to get this: for all x, there exists a y such that P(x,y) is true. Or in plain language, for every
real number x, there is some other real number y such that x*y is positive. That statement also has a definite truth value, namely TRUE. Let's
see why. Where you are sitting right now, pick any real number you like. Now no matter what number you picked, one of three things must
be true about it: It's either negative, positive or zero. I will now tell you the "y" value that will make xy bigger than or equal to zero. If your "x"
was positive or zero, let y = +1. Then x times 1 is positive or zero, which means P(x,1) is true no matter what the choice for x was.
If your x was negative, let y = -1. Since x is negative, x times -1 is positive so P(x,-1) is true. Therefore for every x you might choose,
no matter its value, I can find a y value --- there exists a y value -- that makes P(x,y) true.
What would happen if we had existentially quantified the x earlier instead of universally quantifying it? Well, we'd still need to quantify
the y variable to end up with a fully determined proposition and there are two ways to do that. You could have: "There exists an x such that
for every y, P(x,y) is true" and you could have "There exists an x such and there exists a y such that P(x,y) is true". Now pause the video
and see if you can determine which, if either, of those statements is now true.
"There exists an x such that for every y, P(x,y) is true" is in fact a true statement. The statement is claiming that at least one x exists
such that x*y >= 0 no matter what y you choose, and that's true --- can you guess what x it is?
It's x = 0. If you choose that x, then xy >= 0 for every single y value.
"There exists an x such and there exists a y such that P(x,y) is true" is also a true statement because I can certainly find an example of x
and y where xy >= 0, for example x = 1 and y = 2.
So given a two-variable predicate P(x,y) there are at least four possible ways to quantify it: one for each combination of quantification of x
and y. Each has its own truth value that it's our job, as mathematicians, to explain why the truth value is true or why it's false.
I say "at least" four truth values because in fact sometimes the ordering of the variables matters too. For example look at the predicate
Q(x,y) is the statement that x*y < 1 where the x values are integers and the y values are nonzero real numbers. Look at the statements
for all x there exists a y such that Q(x,y) and there exists a y such that for all x Q(x,y). You might think these statements are equivalent
since all we did was change the ordering of the quantifiers. But look at each one.
The statement for all x there exists a y such that xy < 1 is TRUE, and here's an explanation. Choose any integer x you like. If you chose an
x that was zero or negative, set y = 1 and then xy < 1. If you chose an x that was positive, set y = 1/(x+1). Then xy is x/(x+1) and because the
denominator is bigger than the numerator, the fraction is less than 1. That explanation, notice, does not depend on specific examples --- it
works "for all" x.
However the statement that there exists a y such that for all x, xy < 1... is a FALSE statement. I will explain why no such y exists.
Suppose that we did have a y such that xy < 1 no matter what the x is. This y can't be 0 because 0 isn't in the domain. Given that fact,
it's not the case that xy < 1 "for all" values of x, because there's a counterexample: x = 1/y. If x = 1/y, then xy = 1 and that's not less than 1.
In other words, the order in which we place the quantifiers can sometimes matter! It takes careful mathematical reasoning to see when
these statements are true and when they are false. But that's what this whole course is about, so it's good work.
That brings us to the end of this module on logic. You're learning a lot, so congratulations! Our next module is about two more
fundamental mathematical concepts that underlie computer science: The concept of the *set*, which is the model for all data structures
in computer science, and the concept of the *function* which is the model for all programs. Pretty big ideas, in other words. See you there.