In the last video, we introduced the idea of logic as a way for human beings to  communicate with computers. And we defined
a proposition as a complete thought that has a definite and knowable truth value. In this video, we're going to look at how we can build
complex logical statements out of simple ones using logical connectives.
Look at this basic recipe for peanut butter cookies. It's a list of instructions on how to combine the ingredients and it ends with, "Bake
in a preheated 375 degrees F oven for about 10 minutes or until cookies begin to brown." In some ways this recipe is like an algorithm. It
has input, instructions, and a definite ending point. What triggers the ending of the process in this case? It's not one but two possible
conditions: either the cookies have baked for 10 minutes or they are turning brown. If I were a robot checking the doneness of those
cookies, I'd have to monitor them and the clock and evaluate the truth values of two logical propositions: "Ten minutes have passed", and
"The cookies are turning brown". If either one of those propositions becomes true ---
or if both of them are true --- then I stop the cooking process.
What that last condition in the recipe does, then, is CONNECT two logical propositions with the word "or", making a larger proposition. The
word "or" here is an example of a connective -- an English word that connects two smaller propositions to make that larger one. We
sometimes say that a proposition that cannot be broken down into a bunch of smaller ones is an "atomic" proposition, and a proposition that
isn't atomic --- if it's made up of atomic statements joined by connectives --- is called "molecular".
There are three basic forms of connectives that do this for us.
Maybe we need some part of a computer program to activate if, like in this recipe, any one condition from a list of conditions is true.
Again as in the recipe we usually use the English word "or" to connect the conditions. A statement created by joining two atomic
propositions together with "or" is called a "disjunction". And a disjunction is true, whenever either one or both of the propositions
it joins is true. For example: "Either I passed algebra, or I passed C++" is a disjunction. If you passed algebra but didn't pass C++, the
disjunction is true because the first proposition is true. You were telling the truth in other words when you claimed that you either passed one
class or you passed the other. Same for if you didn't pass algebra but did pass C++. If you passed both, the disjunction is true because if
you passed both, then you definitely passed one. That makes our use of "or" into what we call an "inclusive or", so the "or" statement is
true if either one OR BOTH of the atomic propositions involved is true. The only way a disjunction can be false is if both statements
involved are false. For example if you did not pass either algebra or C++, this statement that you passed one or the other of them is false.
One of the nice things about logic is that the content of the statements involved doesn't really matter, only the form. The truth value of a
molecular statement in other words is always determined only by the truth values of the atomic statements that make it up and the
connectives being used, and nothing else. For example, any time you form a disjunction from two statements,
the disjunction will be true if one or both of the statements involved is true.
This lets us summarize the conditions where a complex statement will be true and where it will be false in a table, like this. Here, the v-looking
symbol is a mathematical symbol used to represent the english word "or". Different symbols represent "or" in different computer
languages, for example the double vertical bars || represent "or" in Java and in C++. In Python you just type the word "or". Since this
disjunction involves two independent Boolean values each of which is either true or false, it leads to four combinations of true/false values.
In each case the truth value of the disjunction is listed in the final column. As we saw, when either one or both of the basic propositions is
true, the disjunction is true. When both are false, the disjunction is false.
This table is called a TRUTH TABLE and we will be seeing much more of these in a minute and in other videos.
Sometimes we need a part of a program to activate if ALL of the conditions in a list are true. For example, to take discrete math you
might need a passing grade in both algebra AND C++, not just one or the other. We use the word "and" and a symbol that looks like an
upside down v to represent this connective, which we call a *conjunction*. In a conjunction of two propositions both propositions must be
true in order for the conjunction to be true. That's summed up in the truth table for conjunctions which you see here. The
conjunction is false otherwise --- that is, whenever one or both of the atomic statements that make up the conjunction is false.
Sometimes we need a part of a program to activate if a single proposition is NOT true. THis is a connective called a negation, and we use
this symbol to denote it. Negations are different than disjunctions or conjunctions because they only work on one statement --- if you have the
statement P, then ~P is its negation. The negation ~P is true when P is false and false when P is true ---
it's the logical opposite of the original statement.
In this video you learned that we form complex logical statements out of atomic statements with connectives. We saw three basic
connectives, "or" (disjunction), "and' (conjunction), and "not" (negation). And we learned about the concept of a truth table
which allows us to see the truth values of a molecular statement as determined by the truth values of the atomic statements and by the
connectives that join them. In the next video we'll look another connective, the conditional or "if-then" statement. See you there.