We've been looking at truth tables as a way to tell when a complex, molecular statement is true based on the truth values of the inputs. In
the last video we saw how to make a truth table for a proposition that has intermediate steps. In this video, we'll wrap up our initial discussion of
truth tables to look at two-variable statements that have multiple intermediate steps, and statements that have three variables.
Let's begin by looking at the proposition "If (P or not Q), then ((not P) and Q)". This proposition has a bit more complexity than
some of the others here and it's not obvious at all when this statement should be true. So let's make a truth table for it.
We'll begin as we normally do, by setting up one column for each of the input variables. Then let's go ahead and make a row for every
combination of the truth values of those inputs. Since there are two inputs, there will be four combinations
and I'm going to put those here in the same order as we have been doing.
Now, just like when we looked at the contrapositive in the last video, we need to build up the main proposition from the bottom
up, like we would do an arithmetic computation with a lot of nested calculations. We'll make one column for each "level" of the statement.
Looking from left to right in the main proposition, I can see that we'll need a column for "not Q". I'll also need a column for "not P"
and I could make that column now, but instead I'm going to continue building up this first part, the hypothesis of the main proposition by
creating a column for "P or not Q".
Again the order in which we set up these columns strictly speaking doesn't matter, but it can make a difference in how well your brain
can keep track of the process, and I find it easier to finish up each part of the main proposition in turn.
So now that the hypothesis of the main proposition is present, let's work on the conclusion. We need a column for not P, and
we need a column for "(not P) and Q". And then finally we need a column for the main proposition.
Let's now fill in each of those columns one at a time. The column for not Q is easy since it's just the opposite of whatever truth value
appears in Q. Similarly, not P is the opposite of P.
Now, for "P or not Q", we have a disjunction. A disjunction is true whenever one or both of the statements involved is true, and false
otherwise. The two statements involved are P, and "not Q" so look at those. Given the information in those two columns, which we
already built, we should have TRUE in rows 1, 2, and 4 and FALSE in row 3.
Now let's do the column for "(not P) and Q". This is a conjunction, which we know is true whenever both statements involved are true
and false otherwise. The statements involved are "not P", and "Q" so look at those columns. They are both true in row 3, otherwise at least
one of them is false. So we have TRUE in row 3 and FALSE elsewhere.
Finally we're ready to fill in the column for the main proposition. This is a conditional statement, and remember, these are true in
every situation except where the hypothesis is true and the conclusion is false. The hypothesis in this case is "P or not Q". The conclusion is
"(not P) and Q". In row 1, the hypothesis is true and the conclusion is false, so put FALSE in the last column. The same is true for rows 2
and 4. In row 3, the hypothesis is false  and in that case we have a TRUE conditional statement.
So there's a complete and correct truth table for this proposition. It's not in principle any different than the others, it just required more
care in building up the table.
But now let's look at something different the statement "If (P and not Q), then R". What's different about this is that there are *three*
atomic statements involved here, not just two. How does that change the truth table? Let's dive in and see.
We are still going to need a column for each of the atomic variables here, so one thing that's different is that there are three of those this
time. Now, what we need is one row for each of the combinations of truth values of these statements. How many rows should there be?
Let's think about it. If we only looked at P and Q and ignored R for the time being, there would be four -- namely these four.
Adding R into the mix here *doubles* the number of rows we need. There is one copy of these four rows needed for the case when R is
true, and another four rows needed when R is false. That's a total of eight rows. That will be the case whenever we have three atomic
variables, again because we need four rows for two variables and then two copies of those four rows, one for each truth value of the new
variable. In fact there's a general principle here: Adding a new variable doubles the number of rows needed in the truth table. If we had a
statement with four variables, we'd need 16 rows --- one copy of these eight rows for when the new variable is true, a second copy for
when the new variable is false.
Now that we have the eight rows needed, we can start putting the proposition together just like usual. Pause the video and try to set up the
columns we'll need, and if you're feeling adventurous, go ahead and try to complete the table you get!
It looks like we'll need a column for not Q, a column for (P and not Q), and then a column for the main proposition. Let's build it up one
piece at a time. Not Q is just the opposite of Q. "P and (not Q)" is a conjunction, true whenever both statements involved are true so that we
should have TRUE in rows 2 and 6 and FALSE elsewhere. In the final column, it's a conditional statement which we know is FALSE when the
hypothesis is true but the conclusion is false, and this happens in line 6 only. Everywhere else either the hypothesis is false or both
statements are true, so there's TRUE there.
So again in principle making a truth table for statements with three or even more variables isn't any different than simple truth tables, other
than the size. We still focus on building up the proposition in a modular way and using the table to keep track.
In the next video, we'll look at something different, the concept of a predicate.