In all of the earlier videos in this module, we've been looking at propositions -- complete statements that have a definite and knowable
truth value. We've seen lots of examples of propositions and learned how to work with them. In this video we're going to re-introduce
an earlier example of something that wasn't a proposition.
Here's that example: x + 5 = 12 . This is a kind of statement, namely it's an assertion that the expression on the left side of the equals sign is
actually equal to the expression on the right. So it's a complete thought; but it doesn't have a definite truth value as is because of that
variable "x". Whether this statement x+5 = 12 is true or not depends on the value of that variable. If x = 10 for instance, then the
statement x + 5 = 12 is false. But if x = 7, the statement is true.
We're going to call a complete statement whose truth value depends on the value of one or more particular variables a predicate.
Predicates are different from propositions. While both predicates and propositions have truth values, the truth value of a proposition
can be known just from the proposition itself without any outside input, while the truth value of a predicate depends on outside input.
Propositions have only one truth value, while in general the truth value of a predicate will be
True for some inputs and False for others -- it depends.
For notation, while we often use letters like P, Q, or R to represent proposition, we affix a variable in parentheses to the letter for a
predicate. For example, could write this to mean "the predicate P with variable x, is the statement that x+5 = 12". We pronounce that
first part "P of x". The allowable inputs for a variable in a predicate is called the domain of the predicate. For example for P(x) here, the
domain could be all real numbers. But here's another predicate: Q(x) is the statement x % 3 = 0 , and for this predicate not all real numbers
might make sense; instead the domain is the set of integers because that's the only thing we can apply the modulus operator to.
Some predicates might have even smaller domains, for example this predicate B(x) = "Prof X has a beard". Apparently "x" represents
not a number but a faculty member now, and since there are a lot of faculty members out there, we might just explicitly state the domain
for example by saying the domain is the set of all mathematics professors at your university.
More formally we would say that a predicate is a function, whose domain is a given set and whose codomain is the set .
This is using some language we have not defined yet, but we'll be doing that in the next module. It just means that a predicate is like a
machine that accepts inputs from a given collection, performs some kind of process, and produces outputs of either TRUE or FALSE.
Predicates are extremely important and useful in computer science, not least because they themselves are like tiny computer programs
with an input of a certain type, and which output either TRUE or FALSE. Here for example is a Python version of our first
predicate. You plug in a real number for x, then go through a process to return either TRUE or FALSE.
Let's look at some more examples of predicates.
S(x) = the length of x is 7
where x is a string, and the domain is the set of all possible strings. Again it's helpful to think of this like a little computer program, like this,
where you plug in a string and get out either TRUE or FALSE. The predicate itself does not have a truth value until something is plugged
in. For example S("Mathematics") is FALSE because the length of that string is 11.
But S("Algebra") is TRUE because the length of Algebra is 7.
Another example: P(x) = x**2 >= 0 where x is the set of all integers. P(x) will be TRUE whenever x**2 >= 0 and FALSE otherwise. So P(2) is true,
for instance because 2**2 is 4 and that's bigger than 0. P(10) is also true because 10**2 is 100 and that's bigger than 0... in fact P(x) is always
true for any input because squaring an integer always returns a result that is nonnegative.
And another example: P(s) = "the length of s is negative" where the domain is all possible strings. Well, this predicate is never true,
because there's no such thing as a string with a negative length.
Generally speaking we can have predicates that are sometimes but not always true, predicates that are always true, and predicates
that are never true. When we talk about how often a predicate is true, this is referred to as quantifying the predicate.
Our next video is going to be all about that idea.
We can even have predicates with more than one variable, like this: P(x,y) = "xy > 0". This requires knowledge of two variables to be able
to determine truth. P(2,3) for example is TRUE because 2*3 is 6 which is bigger than 0.
But P(-4, 5) is FALSE because -4*5 is -20 which is not bigger than 0.
Now you give it a try, from a bit of a different angle. Here's a predicate: P(n) = (3n+1) % 4 = 0. Pause the video now and find as many
values of n as you can that make this predicate true. Come back when you're ready.
I've actually written a Python function here to help me find these. The predicate is here in this first block --- it just implements the process of
returning TRUE if 3n+1 mod 4 is 0 and FALSE otherwise. Down below, I'm going to run a quick loop to go through the integers 1 through 30 to
see which values make the statement true, and maybe I'll see a pattern. It looks like 1, 5, 9, 13, 17, 21... I believe I'm seeing a pattern here that
whenever n is itself congruent to 1 mod 4, this predicate will be true. I'll test that out with some integers outside the range I showed you --- for
example a negative integer, like -3. That's congruent to 1 mod 4, and sure enough my predicate is true. Or 400001 is 1 mod 4, and
that also gives true. So while I can't literally list all of these values, I can put them together in one place and indicate the pattern like so.
This collection, consisting of all the variable values that make the predicate true, is called the truth set of the predicate. For example
for P(x) = x+5 = 12, the truth set is just the single number 7. For P(x) = x**2 >= 0, the truth set is the entire domain, the set of integers.
For S(x) = the length of x is 7, the truth set is the collection of all strings that have length 7.
You've learned a lot in this video: The differences between a predicate and proposition, the domain of a predicate, and the
truth set of a predicate. In the next video, we'll come back to the idea of quantifying a predicate that we mentioned earlier --- that's
taking a predicate and turning it into a proposition by making an assertion about how often the predicate is true