En el último video, aprendimos sobre los predicados, que son como proposiciones pero cuyo valor de verdad depende del valor de una entrada.
variable. Mencionamos brevemente que hay una manera de convertir un predicado en una proposición con un valor de verdad fijo y definido haciendo un
declaración secundaria sobre la frecuencia con la que el predicado es verdadero. Profundicemos un poco más en ese concepto.
Así que aquí está la proposición que vimos por primera vez en el último video: P (x) es la declaración x + 5 = 12 donde el dominio es el conjunto de todos los números reales.
De nuevo, esto es un predicado, no una proposición. Esta afirmación no es ni verdadera ni falsa como es, porque tiene una variable indeterminada.
Pero formemos una nueva declaración que esté relacionada con ella: la declaración "P (x) es verdadera para todos los valores de x". Ahora bien, esta afirmación es definitivamente FALSA
porque sabemos a ciencia cierta que P (x) no es * siempre * verdadero. Es decir, sabemos que x + 5 no es * siempre * igual a 12. De hecho, P (x) solo es cierto para
uno y solo un valor de x, a saber, x = 7. Por tanto, el enunciado "P (x) es verdadero para todos los valores de x" es definitivamente, sabiamente falso. Eso lo convierte en un
proposición, no un predicado.
Aquí hay otra declaración secundaria que podríamos hacer a partir del predicado original: "P (x) es verdadera para al menos un valor de x". Otra forma de decir
esto es que P (x) es * a veces * verdadero. Ahora, esa afirmación es definitivamente VERDADERA porque * hay * al menos un valor de x que hace que P (x) sea verdadero,
e incluso sabemos qué es - x = 7.
Entonces, nuevamente, los predicados por sí mismos no tienen suficiente información para saber si son verdaderos o falsos. A veces decimos que son
underdetermined because the variable prevents us from knowing the truth value. But when we make a secondary statement about
*how often* the predicate is true --- for example "this predicate is always true" or "this predicate is sometimes true" --- these statements are
propositions with truth values. We call this process **quantifying** the predicate.
To approach computer science from a mathematical point of view we often have to make claims about patterns we see or
algorithms we create and then give an explanation. Those claims often come in the form of quantified predicates. For example, in
an earlier video we saw an algorithm that converts a base 10 integer to base 2. We did *not*, however, discuss whether this algorithm
always works. Doing so, involves working with a quantified predicate. The predicate would say, "This algorithm applied to the integer n
produces the correct binary representation". And what we'd want to know, and explain, is whether P(n) is always true. So this notion of
quantifying a predicate is really at the heart of computer science in important ways.
As we saw a moment ago, there's two ways to quantify a predicate. One, like in our example with the algorithm, is to claim that the predicate
is always true. When we take a predicate P(x) and make the claim that P(x) is always true, this is called *universal* quantification. We
have a special symbol for this that looks like an upside down A, which you can remember because this means "for all" x, P(x) is true. For
example, if P(x) is the predicate x+5=12, then "for all x P(x)" is the statement that x+5 = 12 for all real numbers x, and that is a FALSE
statement.
Here are some more examples. Let Q(x) be the predicate x**2 >= 0. "For all x Q(x)" is the claim that x**2 >=0 for every real number x. And
that's actually TRUE this time because we know from basic math that squaring a number always produces a result that's bigger than or
equal to 0.
Here's two more. R(x) is the predicate "The length of x is positive" where x is a string, and S(x) is the predicate the absolute value of x is
negative where x is a real number. Pause the video and find the truth value of for all x R(x), and for all x S(x).
So in these examples, both universally quantified statements are FALSE. It's not the case for every string x, the length of x is
positive because there is such a thing as a string of length 0, namely the empty string. So for all x R(x) is false because we found what's
called a *counterexample* --- a single example that shows us that R(x) is sometimes false, therefore not always true. Likewise for all x S(x)
is false, because there's a counterexample there as well: In fact there are many, for example x = 1. The absolute value of 1 is 1,
which is not negative, so S(x) is not always true.
The other form of quantification we have is when we take a predicate and claim that it is *sometimes*, but not necessarily always true.
For example if P(x) is x+5=12, then while this predicate is not always true, it is true for at least one value of x. A fancier way of saying
this is that *there exists an x* that makes P(x) true. So this form of quantification, where we make a claim about the existence of at least
one input value that makes the predicate true, is called *existential quantification*. We use a special symbol for this too, a backwards "E".
So this notation means, "there exists at least one x such that P(x) is true".
We saw that there exists x such that x+5 = 12, is a TRUE statement. (Remember the universally quantified version of that predicate
was false.) If Q(x) is x**2 >= 0, then since this predicate is true *for all* x, it's certainly true for at least one x.
Now you try it with the earlier predicates R(x) and S(x). Are the existentially quantified versions of those predicates true, or are they
false?
There exists x such that R(x), is TRUE this time because it is true that there exists at least one string that has a positive length. For example,
the word "logic" has a positive length. But, the statement there exists x such that S(x), is false because there does not exist even one real
number whose absolute value is negative.
Here's a table summarizing what we've found in these examples.
So in this video, you learned that taking a predicate and quantifying the variable turns it into a proposition with a truth value. And there
are two ways to do this, universal or existential each of which has its own notation. You also learned that a counterexample can be used to
prove that a universally quantified statement is false. The next video is going to look a little more at this idea of proving quantified
statements are false by asking how do we negate a quantified statement.