Welcome to Module 3 of this course. We've learned a lot so far about the mathematics that computer science is built on. We've learned
how to represent integers in different number bases that make it possible for computers to do math with them. We've also learned about the
logic that both humans and computers use to process information. In this new module we're going to study another fundamental building
block of computer science, the notion of the SET.
We've actually already encountered this idea more than once in the previous videos. For example, when we introduced predicates, we
talked about their "truth set". This was the collection of all input values that makes a predicate true. For example the truth set of the
predicate P(x) which is the statement that x mod 5 is 3, consists of the numbers 3, 8, 13, 18, and so on as well as -2, -7, -12, and so on.
We need a handy and precise way to talk about this collection. And that's what a set gives us.
A set is simply an unordered collection of objects. That's it. There are no restrictions on what can go into a set, and there's no
restriction on the order in which we put things in a set. The only restriction really there is on a set is that we cannot duplicate objects. Once
an object is in a set, we don't put it in twice.
We're using this picture of boxes for this module's videos because boxes are a useful way to think about sets. Sets are just
containers. Anything can go in them. Even other boxes can go inside them --- or they can be empty! The ordering of what's inside those
boxes doesn't really matter. Sets are an extremely simple concept that's wide open for specialized use, and that makes them the
perfect mathematical concept to drive a lot of more complicated computer science concepts of packages and containers.
The objects in a set are often called *elements* of the set. And for notation, sometimes we often use capital letter variables to represent a
set, and we usually use curly braces like these to enclose the elements of a set. For example this set T is the truth set of the predicate P(x)
we mentioned earlier whose elements are the integers that are 3 mod 5. And here's a set S with just three elements, the letters a, b, and c.
And here's a set R that contains four elements that are a mix of numbers, letters, and even other sets. Just like a box you might get when
you buy something might contain other boxes, sets can contain other sets.
Sets are foundational in computer science because every data structure you will ever use in computer science is based on sets. Python
lists and dictionaries for example are not sets (because for example in a Python list, you can have elements duplicated and the order
matters) but they behave like sets and use a lot of the same language to describe them. Any time we use one of these data structures, for
example when we execute a FOR loop, we are working basically with sets.
Sets in mathematics, unlike data structures in computer science, can be both finite or infinite. For example here is a finite set whose
elements are the letters of the English alphabet. And here is an infinite set whose elements are the positive integers. The three
dots indicate a pattern that continues. This set, consisting of all even integers, is infinite in both directions.
As we said, the objects in a set are called "elements" and if we want to say that a particular object is an element of a set we use
this notation here, which looks like an e. This for example says that the number 8 is an element of this set. And this notation here, with
a slash mark through the "element of" symbol, is saying that the number 11 is not an element of this set.
We can even have a set with no elements in it at all. This is called the empty set, sometimes called the "null set", and it's denoted by this
symbol here which looks like a 0 with a line through it. If the idea of an empty set seems weird, just go back to the box metaphor --- it's
not at all weird to think about a box with nothing in it. And that's what the empty set is.
Some sets are so commonly used in math and computer science that they have their own notation. The set of integers, including 0 and
negative integers, often uses this stylized letter Z to denote it. The Z is the first letter in the German word "Zahlen" which means "to count".
Another important set is the set of all integers bigger than or equal to 0. This is called the set of *natural numbers* and it uses this stylized
"N" to represent it. Finally the set of all real numbers, any number at all that can be located on the number line including integers, fractions,
and numbers like pi and square root of 2 that can't be expressed as fractions, is denoted with an R. You can't list those one by one like
integers.
So now you know what a set is, what an element of a set is, how to use curly braces to enclose the elements of a set, what a finite and
infinite set is, what the empty set is, and notation for the special sets of integers, natural numbers, and real numbers. In the next video
we'll look at two different ways to write sets. See you there.