Now that we've learned about sets and taken a good look at set membership, we can introduce two ways of comparing sets in terms of the
elements that they have in common.
Let's suppose we have a set consisting of the names of all the students enrolled in a discrete math class. The professor for that class might
need to send a message out, not to the entire class but just to the first-year students to remind them to go see their advisors. The
group of interest is a portion, but not all of the names in the class. Every person in that group is in the class; but we only want to send the
message to them, not to everyone. In that case what we are using is called a **subset** of the set of all names of students in the class. This
group of first-year students isn't the only subset of the class; we could send messages to all the graduating seniors; or all the students whose
first names begin with a "G"; or all the students who were sitting together at a table on Monday.
Generally speaking, if A and B are sets, then A is a **subset of B** if every element of A is also an element of B. We use this notation, which
looks a little like "less than or equal to" except it's rounded, to indicate A is a subset of B. So for example  is a subset of . And
so is . And even the set  itself is a subset of  because every element of the set on the left is an element of the set on
the right. This means that *every set is a subset of itself*.
Another example would be the natural numbers, which are a subset of the integers because every natural number is an integer;
and the integers are a subset of the real numbers because every integer can be located on the number line. That chain of subset
relations means that the natural numbers are a subset of the real numbers too. The real numbers can have finite subsets as well, for
example the set  is a 2-element subset of the real numbers.
On the other hand, the set  is NOT a subset of  because *not every* element in  is an element of .
We can see that 5, although it's an element of  is not an element of .
Now you try it. Here's a set  (the different letters used in the word "mathematics"). Which of the following sets are
subsets of this? Take a moment and identify them then come back.
Here are your correct answers. The first two sets , and  are subsets because every element in each one is also an element in the
set we started with.  is not, because the letter G is not found in the original set. And the last one is the same as the original set, and
we've alread explained that every set is a subset of itself.
You might have noticed that we can think about subsets using quantifiers, which we learned in Module 2. The definition of subset says that A
is a subset of B if every element of A is also an element of B. IN quantifier language that would say that for all x in A, x is in B. This helps us
think about what it means for a set NOT to be a subset of somethign else. The negation of for all x in A, x in B is the statement there exists an
x in A such that x is not in B. That's why  was not a subset of  --- because there exists an element in
(namely G) that is not in .
Here's another question for you: Is the empty set a subset of ? Pause the video and think about this, and come back
when you've decided yes or no.
This one takes some careful reasoning. We can think of subsets in terms of conditional statements. The statement "for all x in A, x is in
B" can be rephrased as the conditional statement "if x is in A then x is in B." So look at the proposition "the empty set is a subset of
". As a conditional statement this would say "if x is in the empty set, then x is in ". Well, the empty set is
empty, so the hypothesis of that statement "x is in the empty set" is always false. And when the hypothesis of a conditional statement is false,
the conditional statement itself is true. So believe it or not, "if x is in the empty set, then x is in " is true, and therefore
the empty set is a subset of this set. In fact by this reasoning, the empty is a subset of **every** set.
In addition to subset relations, we can talk about whether two sets are "equal". Two sets are equal if they contain exactly the same
elements, like  and . These are equal sets because they have the same elements --- the ordering doesn't make them
different. But it can be hard to tell sometimes if two sets have the same elements. For example, is the set  equal to the set
? One is a finite set and the other is in set-builder notation --- it's hard to tell if the two sets have the same elements just by
looking. So we will say that the set A and the set B are equal if A is a subset of B *and* B is a subset of A.
For example, A =  is equal to the set B = . Here's an explanation. First, A is a subset of B because if x is in A, then x is
either 1 or -1. And in each case, x^2  = 1, therefore x passes the filter given by the predicate in the second set, and x is in B. That
makes A a subset of B. Likewise if y is in B, then y^2 is 1, and a little algebra shows that y^2 - 1 = 0, so (y+1)(y-1) = 0, which means
either y = 1 or y = -1. Therefore the y that was in B, is also in A. That makes B a subset of A. Since they are subsets of each other, they're
equal.
In this video you learned what it means for a set to be a subset of another set, and what it means for two sets to be equal. Those are
basic tools for comparing sets. See you in the next video.