Ahora que hemos aprendido sobre conjuntos y hemos analizado bien la pertenencia a conjuntos, podemos presentar dos formas de comparar conjuntos en términos de
elementos que tienen en común.
Supongamos que tenemos un conjunto que consta de los nombres de todos los estudiantes inscritos en una clase de matemáticas discreta. El profesor de esa clase podría
Necesito enviar un mensaje, no a toda la clase, sino solo a los estudiantes de primer año para recordarles que vayan a ver a sus asesores. los
El grupo de interés es una parte, pero no todos los nombres de la clase. Todas las personas de ese grupo están en la clase; pero solo queremos enviar el
mensaje para ellos, no para todos. En ese caso, lo que estamos usando se llama ** subconjunto ** del conjunto de todos los nombres de los estudiantes de la clase. Esta
el grupo de estudiantes de primer año no es el único subconjunto de la clase; podríamos enviar mensajes a todos los estudiantes de último año que se gradúan; o todos los estudiantes cuyos
los nombres comienzan con una "G"; o todos los estudiantes que estaban sentados juntos en una mesa el lunes.
En términos generales, si A y B son conjuntos, entonces A es un ** subconjunto de B ** si cada elemento de A es también un elemento de B. Usamos esta notación, que
se parece un poco a "menor o igual que" excepto que está redondeado, para indicar que A es un subconjunto de B. Entonces, por ejemplo,  es un subconjunto de . Y
también lo es . E incluso el conjunto  en sí mismo es un subconjunto de  porque cada elemento del conjunto de la izquierda es un elemento del conjunto de
la derecha. Esto significa que * cada conjunto es un subconjunto de sí mismo *.
Otro ejemplo serían los números naturales, que son un subconjunto de los enteros porque cada número natural es un entero;
y los enteros son un subconjunto de los números reales porque cada entero se puede ubicar en la recta numérica. Esa cadena de subconjunto
relaciones significa que los números naturales también son un subconjunto de los números reales. Los números reales también pueden tener subconjuntos finitos, por
ejemplo, el conjunto  es un subconjunto de 2 elementos de los números reales.
Por otro lado, el conjunto  NO es un subconjunto de  porque * no todos * los elementos en  son elementos de .
Podemos ver que 5, aunque es un elemento de , no es un elemento de .
Ahora inténtalo. Aquí hay un conjunto  (las diferentes letras utilizadas en la palabra "matemáticas"). ¿Cuáles de los siguientes conjuntos son
subsets of this? Take a moment and identify them then come back.
Here are your correct answers. The first two sets , and  are subsets because every element in each one is also an element in the
set we started with.  is not, because the letter G is not found in the original set. And the last one is the same as the original set, and
we've alread explained that every set is a subset of itself.
You might have noticed that we can think about subsets using quantifiers, which we learned in Module 2. The definition of subset says that A
is a subset of B if every element of A is also an element of B. IN quantifier language that would say that for all x in A, x is in B. This helps us
think about what it means for a set NOT to be a subset of somethign else. The negation of for all x in A, x in B is the statement there exists an
x in A such that x is not in B. That's why  was not a subset of  --- because there exists an element in
(namely G) that is not in .
Here's another question for you: Is the empty set a subset of ? Pause the video and think about this, and come back
when you've decided yes or no.
This one takes some careful reasoning. We can think of subsets in terms of conditional statements. The statement "for all x in A, x is in
B" can be rephrased as the conditional statement "if x is in A then x is in B." So look at the proposition "the empty set is a subset of
". As a conditional statement this would say "if x is in the empty set, then x is in ". Well, the empty set is
empty, so the hypothesis of that statement "x is in the empty set" is always false. And when the hypothesis of a conditional statement is false,
the conditional statement itself is true. So believe it or not, "if x is in the empty set, then x is in " is true, and therefore
the empty set is a subset of this set. In fact by this reasoning, the empty is a subset of **every** set.
In addition to subset relations, we can talk about whether two sets are "equal". Two sets are equal if they contain exactly the same
elements, like  and . These are equal sets because they have the same elements --- the ordering doesn't make them
different. But it can be hard to tell sometimes if two sets have the same elements. For example, is the set  equal to the set
? One is a finite set and the other is in set-builder notation --- it's hard to tell if the two sets have the same elements just by
looking. So we will say that the set A and the set B are equal if A is a subset of B *and* B is a subset of A.
For example, A =  is equal to the set B = . Here's an explanation. First, A is a subset of B because if x is in A, then x is
either 1 or -1. And in each case, x^2 = 1, therefore x passes the filter given by the predicate in the second set, and x is in B. That
makes A a subset of B. Likewise if y is in B, then y^2 is 1, and a little algebra shows that y^2 - 1 = 0, so (y+1)(y-1) = 0, which means
either y = 1 or y = -1. Therefore the y that was in B, is also in A. That makes B a subset of A. Since they are subsets of each other, they're
equal.
In this video you learned what it means for a set to be a subset of another set, and what it means for two sets to be equal. Those are
basic tools for comparing sets. See you in the next video.