In both math and computer science, whenever we learn about a structure, it's useful to then learn how to build new structures out of it.
We're going to do that now by looking at five operations we can perform on sets that will create new, related sets that can be used for
various purposes.
As a running example throughout this video, suppose you're in a discrete math class. Let's let U be the set of all students in the class. Also
let C be the set of all computer science majors in your class, and F is the set of all first-year students in the class. So C and F are both
subsets of U but we don't necessarily know how C and F relate to each other.
The instructor of the class wants to let all the first-year computer science majors know about the Computer Science club. So she needs to
generate a list of all students in the class who are both computer science students and first year students --- all students who are both in
the set C and in the set F. This is called the *intersection* of those two sets. In general, the intersection of any two sets A and B is a new
set whose elements are those that are elements of A and elements of B. We use an upside-down U symbol like this to represent the
intersection of A and B --- it should remind you of the upside down V we use for "and" when studying logic. We'd express the intersection of
A and B like this in set-builder notation. In our class, C intersect F would contain these three students since they are in both sets at the
same time.
Later on, the instructor gets a message from the university asking her to remind students about signing up for classes. She decides she
needs to especially contact any student that is either a first-year student or a computer science major, since first-year students may
need to be reminded about signing up for classes and computer science majors have a complicated set of courses to finish. So this
time, she needs students who are either first year or computer science majors, or both. This is called the *union* of those two sets. In
general the union of any two sets A and B is a new set whose elements are those that are either elements of A or elements of B or both.
We use a U shaped symbol to denote the union, and here's what it would look like in set-builder notation. For our class, C union F would
contain these eight students since they are in either C or F, or in some cases both.
Not all the students in the discrete math class are computer science majors, and the instructor would like to send the first-year
students who are not majoring in computer science some information about the computer science major to see if they are interested. Now
the instructor needs the students who are first-year students but who are not computer science majors. The set of results is called the
*difference* of the two sets. In general, if A and B are sets, then the difference of A and B is written either with a minus sign A-B, or with a
backward slash A \ B and it's pronounced "A minus B" either way. This is the set whose elements are those that *are* elements of A
*and not* elements of B. In our class, we're looking for students who are first-year students but not computer science majors, so that's F
minus C which in this case has three students in it. Notice that unlike with intersection and union, the ordering matters here. C \ F is
different -- this would be the set of students who are computer science majors and not first year students.
The instructor of the discrete math class decides it would be good to send that information about being a computer science
major to *all* students who are not currently majoring in computer science, not just the first year students. So she needs a list of all
students who are *not* majoring in computer science regardless of what year they are in. This is called the *complement* of a set. In
general, if A is a set, then its complement is a new set whose elements are those that are *not* in A. We use a bar over the name of the
set to denote its complement. In our class, the instructor needs the complement of C, the set of all students not majoring in computer
science. That's this set of seven students. Notice that in order to find the complement, we needed to know what the entire set of students
in the class was. We called that set U, and the set of all elements we are considering in any given situation is sometimes called the
*universe*. So notice that the complement of A is just the difference U minus A; and the difference A minus B is the intersection of A and
the complement of B -- the set of all elements that are in A and not in B.
Back to our discrete math class, it turns out that the computer science department has its own message to send out about class registration to
all first-year computer science majors. So the instructor of the class didn't need to send the information to those students. She needed to
send it to students who are either computer science majors, or first-year students, *but not both*. The set of student in that situation is
called the *symmetric difference* of two sets. In general, if A and B are two sets then the symmetric difference of the two, which we
notate with a triangle symbol, is the union of A and B minus the intersection of A and B --- the set whose elements are either in A or B, but not
in both. In our class, the instructor would need the symmetric difference of C and F, which would be this set.
Now you try it. Let A be the set , B the set , and C the set . Assume that the universe in this case is the
set . Pause the video and write out the following sets in roster notation: A intersect B, B intersect C, A union C, A minus B, A
symmetric difference B, and finally A intersect the complement of B union C.
So A intersect B is the set of elements in both A and B, and that's the set .
B intersect C is the set of elements in both B
and C but there are no elements in both, so that set is empty. Whenever two sets have an empty intersection, we say those sets are
disjoint.
A union C is the set of elements in either A or C or both, so that's . A set union is a
little like merging the two sets and removing duplicates.
A minus B is the set of elements that are in A
but not in B. Well, A consists of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 3,4,5 are in B, so we throw our 3, 4, 5 and are left with . A minus B is like a filtering
process where we start with A and filter out the things that are in B.
A symmetric difference B is A union B, which is , minus A intersect B which is 3,4,5.
Filtering out those three elements leaves us with .
Now for the last one, we build the set piece by piece using order of operations. B union C is the set . The complement of
this is everything in the universe set that isn't in B union C, so that's . Then A intersect with this set is empty, since those two sets
have no elements in common.
In this video we introduced five set operations: intersection, union, difference, complement, and symmetric difference and saw how these
can be used to combine sets in different ways for different purposes. In the next video we'll discuss a sixth operation called the cartesian
product of two sets that produces a very different kind of result.