In the last video we saw a number of operations we can perform on sets to produce new sets that fit different kinds of real
situations. In this video we're going to introduce another set operation that's similar to these, but it's different and needs a little more explanation.
Let's go back to our fictitious discrete math class. Suppose the class has met a total of 10 times and instructor wants to look at attedance
at class meetings. So she creates a spreadsheet with the names of students in one column and the number of days they have
attended in the other. This pairs off each student with a number. We can think of these pairs as an ordered pair, like this. Remember
that U was the set of all students in the class. And the numbers here could range between 0 and 10 since the class has met 10 times. Let's
let A be the set 0, 1, 2, and so on through 10. The set of all possible pairs that the instructor could create, with students in the first slot of
each pair and integers 0 through 10 in the second slot, created is called the Cartesian product of U and A.
In general given any two sets A and B, the Cartesian product of A and B is the set of all ordered pairs that have the first item in the pair
coming from A and the second item coming from B. We use a cross, like you might see in primary school to denote multiplication of two
numbers, as the notation.
For example, look at the set  product with the set . This is the set of all ordered pairs whose first "coordinate" is in the set 1,2,3
and whose second coordinate is in the set a,b. There are six such pairs and here they are: There are two pairs for each of the three
elements of the set  -- (1,a) and (1,b), then (2,a) and (2,b), and finally (3,a) and (3,b).
In our classroom example, the product of U and  is the set of all possible pairings of students and attendance. So there are 11
possible pairs for each student, making this a pretty large set. The pairs that are in the instructors spreadsheet would be a subset of
the entire product but not equal to it.
Now you try it. Write out the set A times B, where A is  and B is the set .
You should find there are eight pairs in this product, and here they are --- four pairs for each element of A. Or another way to think
about it, you have two pairs for each element of B.
Notice that unlike in multiplication of real numbers, the order of A and B in A times B matters. In this example you just worked, B
times A would be this set -- it's still eight pairs and the ordering of the coordinates is reversed. But these are *ordered* pairs --- (x,1) is not
considered to be the same thing as (1,x) so these two sets have the same cardinality, but the elements themselves are not
the same.
You've actualy worked with Cartesian products before because you've worked with ordered pairs before. Back in your early algebra
classes, you learned how to plot points in a two-dimensional xy-plane and then graph functions using this process. Each point is a pair of
numbers, like (4,3) or (-2,-3). So the xy-plane which consists of **all** those points, is the set R times R where R is the set of all real
numbers. This is the set consisting of all possible pairs with real numbers in each coordinate.
So you've learned what the Cartesian product is, and how to find the Cartesian product of simple sets. In our next video, we'll be shifting
gears to focus on the idea of a *function* which, as we just mentioned, is a way of mapping elements of one set onto the
elements of another.